<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A discovery of false teachers and hypocritical preachers.</title>
            <author>Crossley, Thomas.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 62 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 4 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B08867</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">124064150</idno>
  <idno type="VID">192242</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2240941511</idno>
  
            <idno type="OCLC"> 124064150</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C7268AA</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R174385</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocn 124064150</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B08867)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 192242)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books; 1641-1700 ; 2907:15)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A discovery of false teachers and hypocritical preachers.</title>
                  <author>Crossley, Thomas.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>4 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>These are to be sold over against the Rose and Crown at Puddle-dock in London,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1692]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Signed at end: Dated Aug. the 20th, 1692. Thomas Crossley.</note>
                  <note>Imprint from colophon.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: tightly bound with some loss of print.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Cambridge University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="topical_term">Hypocrisy --  Religious aspects --  Christianity --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term type="topical_term">Clergy --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-09 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-07 </date>
            <label>John Latta </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-07 </date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="tract">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:192242:1"/>
            <head>A DISCOVERY OF False Teachers and Hypocritical Preachers.</head>
            <p>THE mark at which all good Designs and Acts take their aim is the Glory of God, and the Good of Man in order to his Glory, and to advance God in his honour, and to promote the welfare of our Souls; and it is from God that all such holy desires, all good <gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>ils and all just works do proceed.</p>
            <p>
               <gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> it be my desire and duty also to love my Neighbour as my self, then it is <gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> duty to do my utmost endeavour that my Neighbour should not be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> by false Teachers no more than I would be deluded by them my self.</p>
            <p>
               <gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>w for the better way and manner of burying the dead, that there may be <gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>ence made between the godly and the ungodly, and that the good word <gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>d may not be so much contradicted as it is, when they bury a wicked <gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> ungodly man or woman they say the same words that they do for most godly, that is, <hi>In sure and certain hope of the Resurrection to eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> Life.</hi> Which is very much contrary to the holy Scripture, that saith, <gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <hi>righteous person shall inherit the Kingdom of God;</hi> as we read more at <gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> in 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.9, 10. And again, <hi>If the Righteous scarcely be saved, where <gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> the Ungodly and the sinner appear?</hi> 1 Pet. 4.18.</p>
            <p>To hear some of them preach agreeable to our blessed Saviour's words, <hi>that <gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> shall be saved;</hi> but according to their saying over the dead Corps, <hi>in sure <gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>rtain hope of eternal life,</hi> there shall be few or none to be damn'd, which <gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>plain contradiction to our Saviour's words: And also contradicts their own <gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>ing, and also it encourageth the By-standers that knew them to be such <gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> as themselves, Swearers, Drunkards, Sabbath-breakers, and the like. They <gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> say, when the Minister says so by them, we need not fear but that we shall <gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> eternal Life as well as they: But perhaps some Minister will say, I did not <gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> that this man was such a bad liver, or such a wicked and ungodly man.</p>
            <p>To which I answer with the words of <hi>Solomon,</hi> Prov. 27.23. that Pastors <gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> to know the state of their Flocks; and not only so, but to be diligent to <gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> it: And also to imitate St <hi>Paul, Act.</hi> 20.20. who kept back nothing that <gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> profitable, but shewed and taught publickly, and from house to house; <gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> that would be a good means to know the state of your Flocks.</p>
            <p>And in the other place, where they also speak against their Consciences, <gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>ing, <hi>As our hope is this our Brother doth.</hi> How can a Minister say, I hope, <gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>e knew him to be a wicked and ungodly man, except he will at the same <gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> say, I hope that the Word of God is not true, or that God is not such <gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> God as he has reveal'd himself to be; but he must as it were make God a <gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>. But I say as St. <hi>Paul</hi> saith, <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.4. <hi>Let God be true, and every Man a <gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>, as it is written.</hi> Again I say, I do not deny the Resurrection of the Body, <gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> the Sadducees do, <hi>Act.</hi> 23.8. but I deny, that all shall arise to eternal Life.</p>
            <p>Another thing is concerning their Christning of Children, as some of them <gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> after such a slight manner, so much contrary to the Canons of the Church, <gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> is, christening them in the House without Godfathers and Godmothers, <gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> without signing them with the sign of the Cross, and without receiving them <gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> the Congregation of Christ's Flock; and when they have Godfathers and Godmothers according to the Canons of the Church, they ought to be such as <gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> received the Sacrament of the Lord's Supper; but they do not ask them <gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> question as they should do. And those that are christened in the Church, it <gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>er the Sermon is done, and all the Congregation is gone, except a very few, <gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>des those that come with the Child. And how can that Child be said to <gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> received into the Congregation of Christ's Flock, when the Congregation <gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>one? They ought to christen them in the time of Divine Service before <gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>on, according to the Canons of the Church: for the Manner ought to <gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> observed of any religious Duty, as well as the Matter it self.</p>
            <p>And how few of them will or do take the care or pains to catechise them, <gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>n they are grown up, as they ought, according to the Canons of the Church; and to have them confirm'd by the Bishop according to the Canons <gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Orders of the Church; or will take the care or pains to examin them, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> they admit them to the Sacrament of the Lord's Supper, whether they <gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> ever catechised and confirmed by the Bishop or no, as they ought to do.</p>
            <p>
               <gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <hi>all things be done decently and in order,</hi> saith St. <hi>Paul,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14.40. <gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> as I find no man ought to take in hand, or presume to alter any common <gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>der in Christ's Church, except he be authorized thereunto.</p>
            <p>Yet notwitstanding this, some will dare to change and alter the Lessons con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to that they are appointed to be read in the Church, and that for malici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and revengeful ends, as it does appear in one reading the 26th Chapter of the <hi>Proverbs</hi> of <hi>Solomon</hi> on the 11th day of <hi>Novem.</hi> on purpose to abuse and call me Fool and Tale-bearer. But I believe, that <hi>Solomon</hi> did not write this Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter for such a bad end, for Ministers to read it for revenge of their own cause, returning evil for good, and to discover their malice in the Congregation, as it is in the 26th Verse of this Chapter.</p>
            <p>But St. <hi>Matthew</hi> writes in the 12 Chapter of his Gospel, Vers. 42. saying, <hi>A greater than</hi> Solomon <hi>is here.</hi> Who saith in <hi>Chap.</hi> 5. <hi>Ver.</hi> 22. that <hi>he that shall say thou Fool, shall be in danger of Hell fire.</hi> And in <hi>Chap.</hi> 23. has denounced no less than 7 or 8 against such hypocritical Preachers, which say and do not, as it is in the 3d and 4th Verses, <hi>Binding heavy and grievous burdens to be born, and lays them on mens shoulders, but they themselves will not move them with one of their fingers,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>The Evangelical Prophet saith something like to this, <hi>Chap.</hi> 9.16. <hi>That the Leaders of this People cause them to err, and they that are led of them are de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stroyed.</hi> And those that will take the pains to look into the foregoing and fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing Verses, may gather out of both something to this purpose. And as it is in <hi>Matth.</hi> 23.13. <hi>They shut up the Kingdom of Heaven against Men; for they neither go in themselves, neither suffer they them that are entring, to go in.</hi> And although our Saviour Christ commanded us in the beginning of this Chapter, saying, <hi>Whatsoever they bid you observe, that observe and do.</hi> And when I did compare this and that where the Prophet saith, <hi>That the leaders of this People cause them to err, and they that are led of them are destroyed;</hi> I thought it was a plain contradiction to our Saviour's Command; and it was some difficulty for me to reconcile them together, or to understand our Saviours meaning: For it did seem strange to me, that he should denounce so many Woes against them in this Chapter, and yet commanded us to observe and do whatsoever they bid us, whether it be right or wrong.</p>
            <p>But with the Assistance of God's Grace, and Holy Spirit, I did find out the true meaning in the Margin of the Bible; the meaning is this: provided always, that they do deliver <hi>Moses</hi>'s Doctrin, which the Metaphor of the Seat sheweth, which they occupied as Teachers of <hi>Moses</hi>'s Learning. Also the Holy Apostle St. <hi>Paul</hi> doth further assist or enform me, saying, <hi>Phil.</hi> 4.8. <hi>Whatsoever things are true, whatsoever things are honest, whatsoever things are just, whatsoever things are pure, whatsoever things are lovely, whatsoever things are of good re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port:</hi> all which does signifie, that our Saviour doth not say or mean, whatso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever they say whether it be true or false.</p>
            <p>Again, God saith to the Wicked, <hi>Psal.</hi> 50.16. <hi>What hast thou to do to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare my Statutes, or that thou shouldst take my Covenant in thy mouth,</hi> seeing thou art but a Hypocrite, as it is further to be proved in the Margin; and again in <hi>Ver.</hi> 17. <hi>Seeing thou hatest to be reformed, and hast cast my words be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hind thee;</hi> and so on four or five Verses more.</p>
            <p>I have heard several Ministers describe an Hypocrite and a Man of a filthy Spirit, saying, Such a Man, or this Man, is of a filthy Spirit, when it is to be feared, that they or he might say to himself, as <hi>Nathan</hi> the Prophet said to the Royal Prophet, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 12.7. <hi>Thou art the Man;</hi> or, thou art the Man that puts on the Picture of a Christian, for an Hypocrite is no more.</p>
            <p>I read and hear several of these false Teachers say, That he that <hi>eateth and drinketh the Flesh and Blood of Christ hath eternal Life, and he will raise him up at the last day;</hi> as it is in <hi>John</hi> 6.54. and several other Verses to that purpose in the same Chapter. But we read in Vers. 60. How <hi>many of his Disciples, when they heard this, said, This is an hard saying, who can hear it?</hi> And in the next Verse we read, <hi>When Jesus knew in himself, that his Disciples mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mured at it, he said unto them, Doth this offend you?</hi> And in Vers. 63. he doth explain it to them, saying, <hi>It is the Spirit that quickneth, the Flesh pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fiteth nothing; the words that I speak unto you are Spirit and Life.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But these false Teachers will take no notice of the latter, which doth ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain the former, as Christ doth, who is the true Teacher; because the latter doth not make so well for their purpose, as those former Verses do, to delude poor ignorant Souls that cannot read, and others that can read, and do not so much mind, as they ought, to prove and try the Truth of what they say. And thus they speak against their own Consciences; for they cannot be igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant of it, that have it in the Chapter before them, <hi>That the Flesh profiteth no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing.</hi> But they think, that if they can but bring a Text of Scripture to co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver their false Doctrin, and to blind Peoples Eyes withal, that it is well enough; although they know that the All-wise God knows their meaning, in bringing such Proofs and leaving others. Thus you may see, that it is not <hi>Whosover eat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth and drinketh Christ's Flesh and Blood</hi> in a gross manner, as they say, <hi>For the Flesh profiteth nothing, it is the Spirit that quickneth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I heard another very false Teacher, say, <hi>That the good Spirit of God does not make us wiser, but better;</hi> which is a very false thing: for I can, with the Assistance of the good Spirit of God, prove that it doth make us wiser, as well as better. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12. We read of <hi>Diversities of Gifts, but the same Spirit.</hi> Also we read, <hi>That the Spirit of Wisdom is one of the first Gifts of the good Spirit of God.</hi> Again, the same Apostle, <hi>Eph.</hi> 1.17. prays, <hi>That God would give them the spirit of Understanding and Revelation in the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of him;</hi> where I gather, that the Apostle would not pray for the Spirit of Wisdom, if it were not attainable: A third proof from the Prophesie of <hi>Isaiah</hi> 11.2. <hi>And the Spirit of the Lord shall rest upon him,</hi> first, <hi>the Spirit of Wisdom and Understanding, the Spirit of Counsel and Strength, the Spirit of Knowledge, and of the Fear of the Lord.</hi> These three Proofs are sufficient to prove, that the good Spirit makes Men wiser, both in Spiritual and Temporal things, as might be further proved by <hi>Solomon</hi>'s Workmen, that had the Spirit of Wisdom given them to do such curious work for building of the Temple.</p>
            <p>And thus we may see what a wicked thing it is, for Ministers to belie the good Spirit of God. I pray you, what is this better than Blasphemy against the Holy Ghost? Is it not pity that suah a false Teacher should be suffered to go into a Pulpit? Also he speaks against reading of Books for a Preparation of the holy Sacrament, saying, It is no matter of reading Books; and he that sticks close to his Work does God as good Service, as he that goes to Church to Prayers: And then in another Sermon puts us upon imitating St. <hi>Matthew,</hi> who, when Christ call'd him from the Receipt of Custom, left all to follow him; as it is <hi>Chap.</hi> 9.9. And then again contradicting himself, puts us upon going to the Publick Prayers of the Church: also he makes little or no dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference between going to the holy Sacrament, and going to hear a Sermon, saying, <hi>Men make a difference where God makes none.</hi> Again he makes as if poor ignorant People, that know not their right hand from their left in mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of Religion, believe that they may come with little or no Preparation to the Sacrament, saying, <hi>What Preparation had the Apostles, when they received every day?</hi> as if they that cannot read, and others that can read, that are as ignorant as they, should be compared to the Apostles; and all this to delude poor ignorant Souls for self-ends.</p>
            <p>I heard another false Teacher say, That he could prove that the Sin against the Holy Ghost may be forgiven upon Repentance; which is contrary to what our Blessed Saviour saith in <hi>Matth.</hi> 12.31, 32. <hi>Wherefore I say unto you all manner of Sin and Blasphemy shall be forgiven unto Men: but the Blasphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my against the Holy Ghost shall not be forgiven unto Men. And whosoever speak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth a word against the Son of Man, it shall be forgiven him: but whosoever
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:192242:2"/> speaketh against the Holy Ghost, it shall not be forgiven him, neither in this World, neither in the World to come;</hi> where we see, that there is no such con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition mentioned, as upon Repentance. Also I have read and heard several say, that those that have sinned that Sin, can never repent; so let him first prove whether ever any did repent of that Sin.</p>
            <p>This he spoke in a deluding way to perswade Men and Women to come to the Sacrament; if they can but perswade them, they do not much matter how they come, prepared or unprepared. Although they can dissemble, preach and set forth Books for a Preparation; yet, for as much as I know by them, they do but dissemble and speak far from the Heart, which is to be feared, that it is for some by-ends and for filthy lucres sake, more than for the Glory of God and the good of Souls, which should be their chief aim, if they had a good meaning. And this is agreeable to what our Blessed Saviour saith in <hi>John</hi> 10. calling them <hi>Hirelings, that feed them only for their own profit and gains, but forsake them in time of danger:</hi> Also he calls them <hi>Thieves, which feed not the sheep, but kill them:</hi> By this and what the Prophet saith before, <hi>That they that are led by them are destroyed,</hi> is plain that they are no better than Murderers of Souls. To this purpose St. <hi>Peter</hi> saith in his 2 <hi>Epist.</hi> 2.3. how they make Merchandize of you, and shall abuse you, and sell you, as they sell Cattel in a Fair, if you have not a care. This I can prove by the Margin to this place.</p>
            <p>Another of these false Teachers told me betwixt him and me, That we have nothing to do with the Law of <hi>Moses:</hi> But since that time I considered with my self, must the Ten Cemmandements be laid aside? For our Saviour Christ saith in <hi>Matth.</hi> 5.17. <hi>Think not that I am come to destroy the Law or the Prophets; I am not come to destroy, but to fulfil:</hi> Again in Vers. 18. he verefies it further, saying, <hi>Till Heaven and Earth pass, one jot or tittle shall in no wise pass from the Law, till all be fulfilled.</hi> For although the Ceremonies were abolish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed at Christ's coming, yet the Precepts were not, but rather confirmed: Why then do Ministers preach out of it, and why are the first Lessons of the Church read out of it, if we have nothing to do with it?</p>
            <p>I observe many things which these hypocritical Preachers speak in the Pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pit against their own Consciences in a dissembling way, putting us upon do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing those things, that they will not do themselves; neither would they have us to do them, bidding us to have a holy Conspiracy against Wickedness, say<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>If we let them alone, how is it to be imagined that God should let us alone?</hi> And yet they can let them alone for this many years, to set forth things to sell in the open Streets on the Lords Day. And when such as I go about to hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der them and amend it, as they bid me; yet, I find none more against it, and against me for doing so, than they are; although they know how God him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self complains by his holy Prophets, That none goes about to amend it, or that dare defend the Truth and shew Mercy to the oppressed; but most Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fessors, so that they be not prejudiced in their Names and Commodities, they care not what be done against the Glory of God: an evident argument, that they never loved him.</p>
            <p>Again how will these Ministers, that put us upon doing such things, ans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer it, when they will neither suffer us, nor do it themselves? But when they see them sit in the open Streets, or in their Houses, Shops or Cellars sel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling things, can pass by and let them alone, winking and conniving at them; and so they are incouraged, when they see Ministers, especially their own, pass by and let them alone; and if they do sometime reprove them, yet that is not sufficient, as we read in 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 2, 3. Chapters, concerning old <hi>Eli,</hi> how he reproved his Sons; but that was not sufficient: But we read further, because he did not restrain them, how God punished him. So these Ministers know that they ought to restrain those that are under their Charge, from evil, and constrain them to good. They know this day should be kept so strict, that <hi>we should not speak our own words, Isa.</hi> 58.13. then how can such buying and selling be suffered on this day? Also they know how that God Almighty has both blessed and hallowed this day; but such Hypocrites, as they and we, do, as much as in us lies, to unbless and unhallow it: For the Prophet <hi>Isa. Ch.</hi> 9.17. saith, <hi>Every one is an Hypocrite;</hi> then what will it be to Ministers and Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strates that suffer such things? As a Bishop writes and confesses, saying, <hi>The higher the Sun is, the less it seems; but the higher that I am in place and office, the greater is my Sin, both in the Eyes of God and others.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now who can judge these to be good Men, whether they be Conformists or Nonconformists, that can endure to see the Lord's-Day thus prophaned in buying and selling and working, by those that are under their Charge and Tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ition? As another of them writes, saying, <hi>When the Name of Christ is blas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemed, or his Truths, Ways, Servants are evil spoken of, contradicted or calum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niated, then ought we to stand up in defence of Christ, and of what is Christ's person or things, to speak as much for them, as others speak agninst them; yea more, to out-speak them and put them to silence, else we should betray Christ and his Cause by our Silence, for that would seem to be a consent, and they would thereby be emboldened to continue, yea to multiply their evil speakings; and weak ones would be occasioned to fall from the Faith, and strong Christians would be much offended, and the Glory of Christ and the Splendor of his Truth would be greatly darkened thereby.</hi> These are very good Sayings, it cannot be denied, and such as ought faithfully to be done; but that which I gather from them is this, that if they do not according to this knowledg which they have decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red and written, or at least do their utmost endeavour, that they do but make the greater discovery of their Hypocrisie: <hi>For he that knows his Masters Will, and does it not, shall be beaten with many stripes,</hi> Luke 12.47. By many stripes I understand is meant the greater punishment they are like to have. Also I ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther from it, that they make our Saviours words good, who says, That they <hi>say,</hi> and <hi>do not;</hi> and where is there a Man to be found, that does <hi>do</hi> as they <hi>say?</hi> Therefore in so saying, they do but as it were, lay heavy and grievous Burdens upon other Mens shoulders. Our loving Redeemer has told us twice in one Chap. <hi>Matth.</hi> 7.16, 20. <hi>How we shall know them by their Fruits;</hi> and that is, by their false Doctrin, evil living and bad Examples; and in the Verse foregoing, bids us <hi>beware of false Prophets, which come to you in Sheeps clothing, but inwardly they are ravening Wolves;</hi> and more at large in the 23, 24 <hi>Ch.</hi> of this Gospel: so that he has left us without excuse. I heartily wish all good Christians to have a great care, that they are not deluded by these false Teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, but take heed how you hear; as our Saviour gives us a caution, <hi>Mark</hi> 4.2<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. and believe not every Spirit. But many are so careless in hearing, that they hear and hear not, being half asleep and half awake, while these false Teachers preach their Souls to Hell: And if they come but once a Week to shew themselves at Church, they think it is enough; and many more there are that come not once a Month, nor once a Year to hear a Sermon; and yet they are let alone to live as they list: But how these Ministers, that have the charge over them, and should be diligent to know the state of their Flock, will or can answer this, I cannot imagin.</p>
            <p>Notwithstanding all this wickedness is done and suffered by them, yet these hypocritical Preachers can have the confidence to call themselves the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sters of Christ. <hi>Let a Man so aecount of us,</hi> saith one, not only as it is ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed to be read as a Lesson in the Church; but he could have the confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence to make choice of it for his Text, saying, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.1, 2. <hi>Let a Man so account of us, as of the Ministers of Christ, and Stewards of the Mysteries of God.</hi> Moreover, it is required in Stewards, that a Man be found faithful: Let a Man so account of us, saith he, of us false Teachers. Now I shall tell you how a Man does account of such as them, I mean St. <hi>Paul,</hi> as it is 1 Cor. 11.13. <hi>For such are false Apostles,</hi> saith he, <hi>deceitful workers, transforming themselves into the Apostles of Christ.</hi> Again he saith, 1 Tim. 4.1, 2. <hi>Now the Spirit speaketh expresly, that in the latter times some shall depart from the Faith, giving heed to the seducing Spirits, and Doctrins of Devils; speaking Lies in Hypocrisie, having their Consciences seared with a hot iron.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Although the holy Apostle St. <hi>Paul</hi> doth say, Let a Man so account of us, that is, of us, that are indeed the true Ministers of Christ and faithful Stew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ards of the Mysteries of God; that will be faithful unto death, as indeed they were; yet he doth not say, Let a Man so account of false Apostles that transform themselves into the Apostles of Christ; nor of false Teachers and hypocritical Preachers. Also St. <hi>Peter</hi> gives a large account of them in his 2 <hi>Epist. Ch.</hi> 2. throughout, comparing them to bruit beasts, and to Wells without water, because they seek to withdraw Men from God to their old Filthiness. Also St. <hi>Peter</hi> and St. <hi>Jude</hi> tells us the horrible Punishment that is prepared for them, <hi>Jude</hi> vers. 14 to 20. Also it is shew'd before, how our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour does account of them in the 7.23. and 24. Chapters of St. <hi>Matth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Again, this hypocritical Preacher saith moreover, <hi>It is required in Stewards, that a Man be found faithful, and that we are forced to commend our selves:</hi> But <hi>Solomon</hi> saith, <hi>Prov.</hi> 20.6. <hi>A faithful Man who can find?</hi> Thus we may see, that if a Man would so account of them as they would be accounted of, and let them alone in their boasting themselves, they will have the confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence and boldness to say, as Christ himself says, <hi>I am the good Shepherd,</hi> Joh. 10.11. and so make themselves equal with him, that was really so. But then they will not, as it is in the latter part of the Verse, <hi>give their Life for the Sheep,</hi> as this good Shepherd and his true Apostles did, for his sake and the Gospels. Now if I should so account of them, and call them good, that are bad; then there is a Wo denounced against me and others that do so, <hi>Isa.</hi> 5.20. <hi>Wo unto them that call evil good; and good evil.</hi> As I have had too good thoughts of them a long time, I pray God forgive me and others, that have better thoughts of them, than they deserve. I must confess, I have rather had hard thoughts of the good Word of God, wherein I have read so many places how they are called false Prophets, false Apostles, and false Teachers; and I could not apprehend them to be so, until it has pleased God, by his good Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence so to order it, that I should find them out what they are, and so by his good Spirit hath opened the eyes of my Understanding, for which great mercy, I give God humble and hearty thanks; also I desire that all others should have the Benefit of it. Another thing I know to this purpose, what a bad thing it is to speak against God's Minsters and Servants; as we have an expamle of God's displeasure against such in <hi>Numb.</hi> 12. where we read, how <hi>Miriam</hi> and <hi>Aaron</hi> spake against <hi>Moses;</hi> therefore I should be very loath to speak or write against these Men, if they were God's Servants and Ministers; but it is sufficiently proved before to the contrary, that they are not so as they profess to be: For what I speak against them, it is for God's Cause, and in his behalf, and for the good and benefit of others, according as some of them have bid me do these three things, saying dissemblingly to this purpose; <hi>Seek the Glory of God, the Salvation of others, and the Good of the Realm.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I heard another False Teacher say, <hi>That we must do according to the Custom of the place where we live, for Peace and Quietness sake:</hi> But I say that this is very much contrary to the Holy Scripture, as may be proved by many Texts of Scripture; but Two or Three may be sufficient. As first, St. <hi>James</hi> saith in his Epistle, <hi>ch.</hi> 4. <hi>v.</hi> 4. <hi>Ye Adulterers and Adulteresses, know ye not that the Friendship of the World is Enmity with God?</hi> Whosoever therefore will be a Friend of the World, is the Enemy of God. And in another place it is said, <hi>Be not conformable to this World, but be transformed into the Image of Christ.</hi> And St. <hi>John</hi> exhorteth us to <hi>Contemn the World,</hi> in his 1 <hi>Epist.</hi> 2.15. <hi>Love not the World, neither the things that are in the World; If any Man love the World, the Love of the Father is not in him, v.</hi> 16. <hi>For all that is in the World, the Lust of the Flesh, the Lust of the Eyes, and the Pride of Life, is not of the Father, but is of the World.</hi> Another Reason he gives in the 17. <hi>v. The World passeth away and the Lust thereof.</hi> And elsewhere it is <gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <hi>That the Godly Followers of Christ, must as it were, go out of the World, beari<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> his Cross.</hi> These Proofs I think are sufficient to prove that we must not do accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the Custom of the place where we live, for Peace and Quietness sake.</p>
            <p>Now I pray you, What Peace and Quietness had Christ and his Apostles when they were in the World? For going about to do good, were so much hated of the World, as we read in the 15. <hi>ch.</hi> of St. <hi>John</hi>'s Gospel, and the 18, 19, and 20. Verses; and so on, <hi>If the World hate you, ye know that it hated me before it hated you. If ye were of the World, the World would love his own, but because ye are not of the World, but I have chosen you out of the World, therefore the World hateth you;</hi> and as it follows, <hi>The Servant <gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s not greater than his Lord. If they have persecuted me, they will also persecute you; but all these things will they do for my Names sake. All this they did without a cause,</hi> as it follows in the 25 Verse. And who were more cruel and malicious Persecutors of Christ and his Apostles, than the Priests, the Chief Priest, and the High Priest; who least ought so to do: And yet they most cruelly persecuted them to Death, or were the chief Causers. And it is to be feared, that if they were upon Earth again, now in these our days, that they would find no better Usage from these malicious Priests, and false Teachers of ours, than they did then. As I find them to be so malicious and spiteful, to such as go about to imitate Christ and his Apostles.</p>
            <p>Another False Teacher, much to the same pupose saith, <hi>No Peace with Men, no Peace with God;</hi> then how does he judge of those that are persecuted to Death for Righteousness sake, as these Holy Apostles, and the Prophets that were before them were? as we read in the fore quoted place, <hi>Mat.</hi> 23. How they killed the Prophets is to be read at large. Now when I did after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:192242:3"/> Meditate on it, I thought it to be a very hard Saying; for if I seek to be Reconciled, and to be at Peace with others, and they will not, Shall I have no Peace with God therefore? will not God accept the Will for the Deed? as it is 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 8.12. Again, the Royal Prophet saith, <hi>When I seek, and speak for Peace, they are for War,</hi> Psal. 120.7. <hi>There is no Peace to the Wicked,</hi> saith God, <hi>Isa.</hi> 57.21. Neither is there any Peace to be expected with them as I read: But this I believe he spoke out of some self-end, it may<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>be, because others were not at Peace with him, or he with them.</p>
            <p>Now these Hypocritical Preachers, can dissemble and speak against the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> for withholding the Bible from their deceived Laity, and training them up in Ignorance and blind Devotion, when they themselves are as bad; but only they would not be seen to be so. It is to be feared, that if Popery should come in amongst us, which God forbid it should, that many of these False Teachers, otherwise called Swearers, that can turn as the Wind turns, would turn, rather than burn for God and his Religions sake. And also it is to be feared, that they would rather have it so, than not, according to what I have heard of them. Nay, it is farther to be feared, that if it should be so, that they would be ready to vote that we might have our Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles taken from us; although they, some of them, can dissemble and say (part with your Lives rather than your Bibles) against their Consciences; as part of the Bible is kept from us, and laid aside (I mean the Margent) as it were an old Almanack out of Date; because there are such things in it against them, that they would not have us to know, and so they keep us as igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant as they can, that we may not find them out what they are: As they say, it is for that reason that the Papists do withhold the Bible from their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived Laity, that are so much deluded by them: Yet they can Pray and Preach against them as they do. I do not question but that the Papists can say something against them; if they cannot, I can, as is here to be seen: And I have read something what they say against them again: They say that the Papist both adds, and diminishes from the Word of God. First, they add in making Seven Sacraments, that is Five more than we read of in Holy Writ that Christ has instituted; and then they diminish, in leaving out the Second Commandment, and splitting another in Two, to make up the Number Ten.</p>
            <p>They may say the same of us that are of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> for a great many of us, if not the most part, doth add and diminish from Gods Holy Word and Commandments, to my Knowledge, as I can make it appear with Gods Assistance; for God has allowed us Six days for our Worldly Business, and left himself but One day in Seven, for his Worship and Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice: Yet how many of us are there that do not diminish and rob God of that One day, and add it to the Six days that he has allowed us? And I think the like may be said of all the rest of the Commandments in one re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spect or other.</p>
            <p>Thus we may see that one Perswasion needs not judge and condemn a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother so much as they do: For as the Apostle <hi>Paul</hi> saith, <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.1, 2, 3. <hi>Thou art inexcusable O Man, whoever thou art, that judgest, for wherein thou judgest an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other, thou condemnest thy self; for thou that judgest, doth the same things: But we are sure that the Judgment of God is according to Truth, against them which commit such things. And thinkest thou this O Man, that judgest them which do such things, and doth the same, that thou shalt escape the Judgment of God?</hi> Also the Apostle in his 1 <hi>Epist.</hi> to the <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.10. beseecheth all by the Name of <hi>Brethren, and by the Name of our Lord Jesus Christ, that ye all speak the same thing; and that there be no Divisions among you, but that ye be perfectly joyned together in the same Mind and in the same Judgment.</hi> And not to contradict one another; as they do not only contradict one another, but themselves also, both in their Preaching, and in their Lives and Conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sations also, as I see and hear, by their frequenting the Coffee-Houses, and other Publick Houses, so much as they do both Day and Night; so that the Watchmen of the City, find them out at One or Two of the Clock in the Morning: But for Modesties sake, I will not say the worst that I could say. But these things contradict their Preachings, and make it no better then Nonsense: As they can tell us, to be Hearers and not Doers of the Word, is Nonsense; so I say to them, to be Preachers and not Practicers, that is Nonsense. I think the best Preaching, would be for Ministers to walk more circumspectly themselves, and to give good Examples to others, and no bad ones, as they do a many.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Some indeed,</hi> as the Apostle St. <hi>Paul</hi> saith, <hi>Preaches Christ, even out of Envy, Strife and Contention; not sincerely,</hi> Phil. 1.15, 16. saying, <hi>Let a Man abide in his Calling wherein he is called,</hi> 1 Cor. 7. Twice in this <hi>Chap.</hi> 20. and 24. al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>most the same Words, saith one, which I know his Meaning was to me, <hi>A <gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>rm and no Man;</hi> as it is in <hi>Psal.</hi> 22.6. in comparison of some Men. <gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ut in comparison to Almighty God, I may say as <hi>Abraham</hi> said, <hi>but Dust and Ashes,</hi> Gen. 18.27. Yet saith he, <hi>Let a Man abide in his Calling;</hi> as an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other before said to the same Purpose, endeavouring to Preach us away from the Prayers of the Church: Thus they Preach out of Self-ends, <hi>out of Envy, Strife and Contention; not sincerely.</hi> But although St. <hi>Paul</hi> doth say, <hi>Let a Man a bide in his Calling,</hi> yet he doth not forbid us to do other Christian Duties for God and our Neighbours, but puts us upon it, saying, <hi>Let no Man seek his own, but anothers Wealth;</hi> as it is in this same <hi>Epist.</hi> Chap. 10.24. But what I do here, is for the good of others; yet every one that I speak with about it, is against me, and not only against me, but against God; so that I may say as the Psalmist saith, <hi>Who will rise up for me against the Evil Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers? or who will stand up for me against the Workers of Iniquity,</hi> Psal. 94.16.</p>
            <p>I read what the Prophet <hi>Malachi</hi> saith in his First and Second Chapters, chiefly against the Priests, for being Seducers of the People, and their Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kindness and Profaneness, Irreligiousness, Negligence, Covetousness, and Evil Examples; and that they served God after their own Fantasties, and not according to the Prescript of his Word, as they ought to do. And elsewhere I read of the Scandalous Neglect of Ministers: And who brings a greater Scandal upon Gods true Religion than they do? And in another place, <hi>What is worse then a covetous Man?</hi> And St. <hi>Paul</hi> saith <hi>Eph.</hi> 5.5. <hi>For this ye know, That no Whoremonger, nor Unclean Person, nor covetous Man, who is an Idolater, hath any Inheritance in the Kingdom of Christ and of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Again, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.3. <hi>Through Covetousness, shall they with feigned words, make merchandise of you, whose Judgment now, of a long time lingreth not, and their Damnation slumbreth not.</hi> And in the 14. <hi>v. Having Eyes full of Adul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dultery, and that cannot cease from sin, beguiling unstable Souls; an heart they have exercised with covetous Practice, cursed Children: Which have forsaken the right way, and are gone astray, v.</hi> 15. <hi>following the way of</hi> Balaam the Son of <hi>Bosor, which loved the wages of unrighteousness.</hi> And the Prophet <hi>Jeremi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ah,</hi> hath pronounced a Curse to <hi>them that do the work of the Lord, negli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gently or deceitfully,</hi> Ch. 48.10.</p>
            <p>Another thing that I observe is, How these False Teachers, when they Preach Funeral Sermons, and in the behalf of the Poor, how they will then stretch their Consciences. First in the Praise of the Deceased Party to please their Friends, and as they speak against their Consciences when they bury them, so likewise when they Preach their Funeral Sermons.</p>
            <p>The next is in the behalf of the Poor, much like the Papist, that makes them believe that they merit by their Good Works, and by their Charity. So do our False Teachers say, that our <hi>Charity covers a multitude of Sins;</hi> when it is the Charity of Christ that covers a multitude of Sins: Then what is that, but as much as to say, That we merit by our Charity? For what is <hi>given to the Poor is lent to the Lord,</hi> say they; whitout putting in the word <hi>if.</hi> As they should say, <hi>If you come lawfully and honestly by it, and if you do all other Religious Duties that Almighty God requires of you, as Christians ought to do; and do no wicked thing that God has forbidden you,</hi> then I say, if they did say thus, then they would not speak against their own Consciences as they do, both in the Pulpit and at the most Holy Sacrament; using such like Expressions, without saying <hi>if:</hi> But as it is said, <hi>You that are Teachers of others, have need that some should teach you,</hi> As St. <hi>Peter</hi> and St. <hi>Jude,</hi> in their Epistles before mentioned, comparing them to <hi>Beasts,</hi> and charging them with <hi>Ignorance;</hi> saying, <hi>They speak evil of those things which they know not.</hi> But in this it is not so much through Ignorance, as it is against their Knowledge; which is far worse. Again, They say that our <hi>Righteousness hides a multitude of Sins,</hi> when it is the Righteousness of Christ; and so de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogates from God. Now what is our Righteousness, the best of us <hi>but as filthy Rags,</hi> in comparison of Christs Righteousness? Again, when we have done all that God hath commanded us, we must confess that we are but <hi>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>profitable Servants:</hi> For we have done but that which was our Duty to do, <hi>Luke</hi> 17.10. How then can they say, or we think that we merit? Now I do not mention all this to hinder the Poor, <hi>For with such Sacrifices God is well pleased,</hi> if they be done as they ought to be, with Holiness and Righteousness of Life; but I do mention this, to shew what False Teachers a many of them are.</p>
            <p>Now let us suppose that a High-way Man that robs a Man of a great Sum of Mony, should come to Church and give a small part of that to the Poor, only <hi>to be seen of Men, as the Hypocrites do,</hi> Will this be acceptable to God think ye? and yet I believe that there are many worse Thieves, that wrongs and oppress the Poor, under a Pretence of their Charity; as the Governours of the Hospital of <hi>Bethlem</hi> do: For I never heard that the High-way Men do pretend Charity in what they do, as these wicked Men do, to deceive the World by.</p>
            <p>Agan, There is a Woe denounc'd against the Rich, <hi>Luk.</hi> 6.24. I mean against such as get their Riches by unlawful means, as Fraud and Oppression; making themselves Rich, and others Poor: And no less Woe be to them that suffer such Oppression when they are inform'd of it, and will not do their Duty. Remember what the Bishop saith before; the higher that a Man is in Place and Office, the greater is his Sin again, if they make no good use of their Riches for Gods Glory and the good of others.</p>
            <p>Hear what God Almighty saith by the Mouth of the Prophet <hi>Hosea,</hi> ch. 5. v. 1. O <hi>ye Priest hear this, and hearken ye,</hi> O <hi>House of</hi> Israel, <hi>and give ye ear</hi> O <hi>House of the King,</hi> (meaning <hi>Jeroboam) for Judgment is toward you, because you have been a Snare on</hi> Mizpah, <hi>and a Net spread upon</hi> Tabor. And in the Margent it is said, <hi>That the Priests and Princes catched the Poor People in their Snares, as the Fowlers did the Birds in these Two Mountains.</hi> Notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing they seemed to be given altogether to Holiness and to Sacrifices, which here he calleth <hi>Slaughter</hi> in the 2. <hi>v.</hi> in Contempt, <hi>Though I have been a Rebuker of them all,</hi> saith the Prophet: Then how will Magistrates and Ministers answer these things, <hi>when the Kings of the Earth,</hi> as it is <hi>Rev.</hi> 6.15, 16, 17. Verses, <hi>and the great men, and the rich men, and the chief Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains and the mighty men; and every Bond-man, and every Free-man hide themselves in Dens and among the Rocks of the Mountains, and say to the Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains and Rocks, fall on us, and hide us from the Presence of him that sitteth on the Throne, and from the Wrath of the Lamb: For the great day of his Wrath is come, and who can stand?</hi> This is not meant to the Godly, but to the Wicked and Ungodly. Now if I know these things by them, and do not utter them, then I am accessary to their Sins, and so should make my self Partaker with them, in not discharging my Conscience.</p>
            <p>We read how the Prophet <hi>Malachi</hi> hath pronounced a Curse against such a <hi>Deceiver, that hath in his Flock a Male, and voweth and sacrificeah unto the Lord a corrupt thing, Chap.</hi> 1.14. And is it not so with those that go to the Church under a Pretence of Religion and Charity, and give naughty Mony to the Poor, that is to say, Brass or Clipt Mony. Is not that a corrupt thing? for what is given to the Poor, is, or should be lent to the Lord; And will such naughty Mony be acceptable to God think ye? And yet I see some do give Clipt Mony at the most Holy Sacrament; and as we read more at large in the same Chapter, how <hi>the Priest and People were both weary of serving of God,</hi> and passed not what manner of Sacrifice and Service they gave to God: For that which was least profitable, was thought good enough for the Lord. So I think it is a great Sin to those that take Clipt Mony, and a greater to those that suffer it to pass, because thereby the Clippers are encouraged to venture their Lives; as they do both venture and lose their Lives: Then are not such Incouragers guilty of their Death? For if every one would refuse to take it as I do, then to be sure they would give over Clipping; and it seems to me an unreasonable thing, that they should Dye for it, when they are so encouraged in it, and it might be so easily prevented.</p>
            <p>Another thing I have observed, how ready some People are to make a lie, and put it into the mouths of their Children and Servants, fearing Men more than God; but <hi>Solomon</hi> tells us, <hi>The fear of man bringeth a snare,</hi> Prov. 29.25. Again it is said in the Margent, <hi>He that feareth Man more than God, falleth into a snare, and is destroyed.</hi> Again, the Prophet saith, <hi>Who art thou, that shouldst fear a mortal man, and the Son of man which shall be made as grass,</hi> Isa. 51.12. Thus we may see what a bad thing it is for any to fear Man more than God, but much worse for Ministers to do so, and to give such bad Examples in their Families; and yet I find none more ready to do so than these false Teachers are, and to make a lie and put into their Servants mouths to deny
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:192242:4"/> them to those that go to speak with 'em; although they say in the Church, <hi>Come unto me or some other discreet Minister of Gods word:</hi> Yet they will not suffer us to come, as they say, to be resolved of some doubts or scruples, as it is their duty so to do. But let such, as will dare to make a lie, take notice what St. <hi>John</hi> saith in <hi>Rev.</hi> 22.15. <hi>For without are Dogs, and Socerers, and Whoremongers, and Murderers, and Idolaters, and whosoever loveth and maketh a lie.</hi> Again St. <hi>John</hi> saith in his 1st <hi>Epist. ch.</hi> 4. <hi>ver.</hi> 1. <hi>Believe not every Spirit, but try the Spirits whether they are of God;</hi> and he giveth a good reason for it, <hi>because many false Prophets are gone out into the World.</hi> Vers. 2. it is said, <hi>Every Spirit that confesseth that Jesus Christ is come in the flesh, is of God.</hi> And in Vers. 3. he saith the contrary, <hi>Every Spirit that confesseth not that Jesus Christ is come in the flesh, is not of God.</hi> These two last Verses, and other such like Texts, as speak in the general, do these false Teachers make use of to delude poor ignorant Souls withal. The Devil can bring Texts of Scripture to delude Souls with; as he did attempt and do his endeavour to our blessed Saviour Christ, although he knew he was God as well as Man, and knows all things, and cannot be ignorant nor deceived, <hi>Matth.</hi> 4.6. <hi>If thou be the Son of God cast thy self down; for it is written, he shall give his Angels charge concerning thee, and in their hands they shall bear thee up, least at any time thou dash thy foot against a stone.</hi> So do these false Teachers, who are the Devils Instruments, bring such Texts of Scriptures as make best for their delusions. Every one say they, <hi>that confesseth that Jesus Christ is come in the flesh, is of God:</hi> I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve St. <hi>John</hi> does not mean every one that <hi>says</hi> they believe and confess Christ, for the Devils and these false Teachers do confess and profess as much; but it is only they that <hi>do</hi> their utmost endeavour to live up to what they confess and profess to believe. Our Saviour saith, <hi>Not every one that saith unto me, Lord, Lord, shall enter into the Kingdom of Heaven; but he that doth the Will of my Father which is in Heaven,</hi> Matt. 7.21. This seems to contradict St. <hi>John,</hi> who saith, <hi>Every Spirit that confesseth that Jesus Christ is come in the flesh, is of God;</hi> and if I leave it so, some may say that I go about to make St. <hi>John</hi> a Lyar; no, I do not go about to contradict the holy Scripture, though I go about to prove these false Teachers Lyars, like their Father the Devil: But I believe St. <hi>John</hi> does not mean every one that confesseth Christ in the Church or Pulpit, and then denies him when they are out, by their evil living and bad exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples; but rather, every one that confesseth Christ at all times, in all places and upon all occasions, and never for fear of Men deny him in any troubles, suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferings or persecutions whatsoever.</p>
            <p>The like may be said concerning the word <hi>All,</hi> which some of these false Teachers use more than is right, on purpose to delude poor ignorant People, soothing them up in their Sins, saying, that Christs Birth, Death, Resurrecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and Ascension is for the benefit and Salvation of <hi>All;</hi> which they speak ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry much against their Consciences: For they know, that it is only to those that do truly and sincerely repent of all their sins, stedfastly believe in his holy Name, and wholly trust and relie on him and his mercy in the forgive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness of all their sins, in his Blood and the Merits of his most precious Death and Passion on the Cross; and truly love and fear him, and obey his holy Gospel in all things, as near as we can. But instead of dealing thus truly and faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully with us, they do but flatter and dissemble with us, making the best of things, and making them as easie as they can; seeking to please Men more than God: But the holy Apostle St. <hi>Paul</hi> saith, <hi>If I seek to please men, I am not the Servant of Christ, Gal.</hi> 1.10. Again in 1 <hi>Thes.</hi> 2.4. <hi>Even so, we speak, not as pleasing Men but God;</hi> not seeking the praise of Men, as these do; but suppose they have the praise of Men, they have not the praise of God, as is to be proved at large in the 23, 24th Chapters of St. <hi>Matthew.</hi> Now I reckon that the Passion of Christ will be no benefit nor signifie any thing to the Salvation of their Souls, that continue obstinate and disobedient to the Commands of Christ; but rather a greater condemnation to all that will not comply and sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit to his holy Will: Thus ought these false Teachers to say, rather than to make ignorant People believe, that he died for all.</p>
            <p>It may be, it will be a hard thing to make my Friends and Neighbours be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve these things to be true against them; but you may as well say, that you will not believe the Word of God to be true, if you will not believe me. I would have you believe <hi>Moses</hi> and the Prophets in the Old Testament, and Christ and his Apostles in the New. I will not say as one saith, <hi>Blame not me, but blame them that say so,</hi> lest I should bid you speak Blasphemy against the Holy Ghost: For St. <hi>Paul</hi> tells us, that <hi>all Scripture is given by inspiration of God, and is profitable to teach, to convince, to correct, and to instruct in Righteous<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness,</hi> 2 Tim. 3.16. Therefore he might rather have said, blame not me, but blame the Prophets and Apostles that say so, if you will or dare speak Blasphemy agaist the Holy Ghost: For I suppose he knows, that these holy Men spake by the Inspiration of the Holy Ghost; and so he might have given ignorant People to understand, what it is to speak against such holy Men, as it is his place and office to inform and instruct the ignorant, and not to bid them speak Blasphemy.</p>
            <p>Now I have something against the Clerks: When the Ministers are so bad, <gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t is not likely their Clerks should be very good; for I have observed, how they have often set forth such a Psalm, as not only causes themselves, but the Congregation to say or sing a false thing, or against their Consciences: as in the 5th part of 119. <hi>Psal.</hi> Who is it that can truly say, they love and fear no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but God? when it is an hard matter to find one that doth so; and in most parts of this Psalm there are such expressions, if seriously considered, very few can truly say them without speaking against their Consciences.</p>
            <p>I heard a Clerk that sung this 119th Psalm throughout, at sundry times, and in the third part there is a Curse he pronounced against those that do not Gods Hests attend upon. Now I think that Publick Prayers is one of Gods Hests; if this is to be taken in a strict sense, that is to say, to attend on them both morning and evening constantly, then who is it that is not cursed? For I see that neither the Ministers, I mean the head-Ministers, nor their Clerks do so constantly both morning and evening attend this Ordinance, as they should, to give good Exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples to others; but rather discourage others by seeing them absent: Neither are they willing to have a Psalm, or part of one, to be sung at Prayers; but as I have seen several of the Readers, not only refuse when it has been offered to them, but forbid the Clerks, although they know the Psalmist says, <hi>What a good thing it is to sing Praises to God;</hi> yet at several Churches, as I know, they do not sing Psalms at the Sacrament, which is the highest Ordinance of the Gospel, and the principle part of God's Worship; so that I think we ought then more especially to sing praises in way of thankfulness to Almighty God for so great a mercy in giving us his only Son to be a Sacrifice for us miserable Sinners. But I see they do in this, as they do in other parts of God's Worship and Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, as slightly as they well can. Also I see how malicious some of the Clerks and other Servants are, even at the time of the Sacrament before the commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicants are gone, which is a very sad sight to see; I pray God forgive them their Malice to me.</p>
            <p>Again concerning the Curse which I heard the Clerk pronounce against those <hi>that do not Gods hests attend upon;</hi> some may or will think it a very hard say<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, if we consider these things following: as first, if a Man be under banish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and so cannot come to the House of God as he would, as <hi>David</hi> him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self was, as it is mentioned in the 84 Psalm, when he was driven forth of his Country, desired most ardently to come again to the Tabernacle of the Lord, and the Assembly of the Saints to praise the Lord. And also the Apostles, but more especially St. <hi>Paul,</hi> who was kept under confinement for some years, so that he could not go, as he used to do or would have done: Or if a Man be in a Journy, or so tied to days work, that he cannot go, but yet would go if he could; in such cases, I do not doubt, but that God will accept of the Will for the Deed; for though a Man be absent in body, yet his heart may be there. But on the contrary, those that have time and opportunity, and might go and will not, but rather spend there precious time in the Ale-houses, other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise called Hell-houses or the Devil's Schools, where there is such swearing, cursing and gaming, and a great deal of more wickedness and prophaness used; such, I say, I cannot imagin how they can escape this Curse, as it is in <hi>Heb.</hi> 2.3. <hi>How shall we escape damnation, if we neglect so great salvation?</hi> We read <hi>Act.</hi> 17.11. how the wicked Jews were converted, and <hi>received the word with all readiness of mind, and searched the Scriptures daily, whether those things were so:</hi> Also we may further understand what was the happy effect of it; for in the next Verse it is said, <hi>Therefore many of them believed:</hi> and then shall they not rise up in Judgment against those that will neither read them at home, nor go to the publick Prayers of the Church daily to hear them read, when they might as well go as not?</p>
            <p>Again, I have heard one of our false Teachers say, <hi>He that goes to Church and gives not something to the Poor, does but half his duty;</hi> then what do those, that instead of giving, rob the Poor of part of that that is given? This I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve he spake out of some self by or base end; for I heard one of the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants of the Church say, that <hi>he can preach to others for Charity, and give none himself.</hi> Again, where it is not to be had, God does not require it; al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though I know that God did require it in the Law of <hi>Moses,</hi> saying, <hi>None shall appear before the Lord empty, Exod</hi> 23.15. <hi>Deut.</hi> 16.16. But that was at the three great solemn Feasts of the year: Thus we may see, how they put others upon those things that they will not do themselves.</p>
            <p>Now I have something to say against the Dissenters or Nonconformists, that behave themselves so irreverently in the place of their Worship: I have seen the Minister go into the Pulpit with his hat on his head, and after the Sermon put his hat on again in the Pulpit, which seems to me a very unseemly thing: But perhaps some will say, where is there any Text of Scripture that speaks expresly against it? To which I answer, if there be none that speaks expresly, yet there are several that speak to that effect: as in <hi>Exod.</hi> 3.5. where God commanded <hi>Moses,</hi> saying, <hi>Pull off thy shoes from off thy feet,</hi> with this reason annexed, <hi>for the place whereon thou standest is holy ground;</hi> and another reason is in the Margent, that is, <hi>because of my presence.</hi> Also God hath said, <hi>That whereever two or there are gathered together in my name,</hi> Mat. 18.20. <hi>there am I in the midst of them:</hi> Then is not his presence to be reverenced; and if his shooes were to be put off, is it not likely his hat also? Besides, I heard a Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nister say, that it might be meant his hat. Again, the holy Apostle St. <hi>Paul</hi> reproves Men for praying in their holy Assembly with their heads covered, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11. and at the 14 <hi>ver.</hi> he saith, <hi>Doth not even nature it self teach you; that if a man have long hair, it is a shame unto him?</hi> And so I say, doth not even very Nature it self teach you, that it is a shame for Men to have their hats on their heads in their holy Assemblies, but more especially in the Pulpit? Also they suffer their Auditors to have their hats on their heads in Sermon time; and not only so, but in Prayer time too, as I have seen some, when the Minister begins his Prayer, instead of puting off their hats, put them a little on one side; so that they wear them on their heads still, and might as well be on as they were: They also suffer them irreverently to sit in Prayer time, and neither stand nor kneel, as they ought to do, as it is to be proved in <hi>Psal.</hi> 95.6. <hi>O come, let us worship and bow down; let us kneel before the Lord our Maker.</hi> And how disobedient are the Ministers to the Command of Christ in not saying the Lords Prayer, but speaking against a form of Prayer? Now I never read that Christ spake against a set form of Prayer, but when one of his Disciples said unto him, <hi>Lord teach us to pray, as</hi> John <hi>also taught his Disciples, Luk.</hi> 11.1. he made no reply a<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gainst it, but immediately taught them saying, <hi>ver.</hi> 2. <hi>When ye pray, say, Our Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther which art in Heaven,</hi> &amp;c. For it is likely, if he would ever have said any thing against a form of Prayer, it would have been then; but instead of saying any thing against it, he rather did allow and approve of it; for if he had not, to be sure he would not have taught his Disciples one, and in them, us; and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded them and us to say it; and when he did say, <hi>say it,</hi> he did not say, <hi>say it on a Book;</hi> for if he had said so, then how should a blind Man say it, or another in the dark, or a Man that cannot read? Then it follows, that those that will not say it but upon a book, are too superstitious therein. I have observed, that one of our Ministers would not say the Lords Prayer, but upon his Book, which I could not imagin what should be his meaning, except he did it to countenance a form of Prayer; if it were so, I think it were well enough.</p>
            <p>But another thing is, he would have all the Congregation to say after the Minister, <hi>Amen,</hi> so as to make the Church ring again; but it is said, that <hi>the Prayer of the wicked is an abomination to the Lord;</hi> then I would gladly know what it is for us to joyn in Prayer with such dissembling Hypocrites, as are here discovered, and say <hi>Amen</hi> to their abominable Prayers? Now, I do not deny, but that we ought to say <hi>Amen,</hi> if we had true Ministers, such as St. <hi>Paul</hi> and the rest of the holy Apostles were: But now our false Teachers and hypocritical Preachers, whether they be Confomists or Nonconformists, have great need to pray with St. <hi>Paul, That while they preach to others, that they themselves do not become cast aways,</hi> 1 Cor. 9.27. which I pray God they may not. So I conclude with the Caution that our Blessed Saviour gives in <hi>Matth.</hi> 24.4. saying, <hi>Take heed that no man deceive you.</hi> To all this might be added the Collect that is read on St. <hi>Matthias</hi>'s day; but I do not write it here, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bause I would not have Men to read it so irreverently with their hats on their heads. I rest,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Yours in the Lord, <hi>Thomas Crossley.</hi>
               </signed>
               <dateline>Dated <date>
                     <hi>Aug.</hi> the 20th, 1692.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>These are to be sold over against the <hi>Rose</hi> and <hi>Crown</hi> at <hi>Puddle-dock</hi> in <hi>London.</hi> Price 2 <hi>d.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>